Finding Aid for Margaret Leutheuser Collected Papers [microform] 1853-1935
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Margaret Leutheuser Collected Papers [microform] 1853-1935
Leutheuser, Margaret.
1 microfilm roll
Papers collected by Margaret Leutheuser of Ann Arbor, Michigan, relating to ancestor families, notably the Leach, Waterman, and Armstrong families. Civil War materials of Morgan L. Leach, member of the 1st and 9th Michigan Cavalry; farm account books of Edgar and William Armstrong of Mundy Township, Genesee County, Michigan; correspondence of other family members; and scrapbooks containing newspaper accounts of settlement of Leach family in Genesee County, and account of trip of Morgan Leach to Traverse Bay, Michigan, in the 1860s.
85255 Aa 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
These materials were acquired in 1981 from Margaret S. (Mrs. Richard A.) Leutheuser (Donor no. 6570 )
The collection is open for research.
The collection was microfilmed in 2000. Access to the originals is restricted.
Most of the collection relates to the descendants of Jeshuran and Theoda Huntington Leachnatives of Vermont who, after their marriage, moved frequently with their family between Ohio, Michigan and New York states. Following Jeshuran's death in c. 1842 the family returned to settle in Genesee County, Michigan. There were seven children: Morgan L., DeWitt Clinton (called D.C.), Henry, Lois Huntington, Wesley, A. Judson (called A.J. or Judson), and Theoda.
Morgan studied medicine at the University of Michigan in 1851-1853. He practiced medicine and married before returning to complete his studies in 1857-1858, when he received his M.D. Morgan enlisted in the 1st Michigan Cavalry in 1861 as a private and was soon made a hospital steward. He was wounded in 1861, taken prisoner, paroled and given a medical discharge. He was commissioned in late 1862 as Assistant Surgeon with the 9th Michigan Cavalry. He resigned on July 15, 1864 and returned to Michigan where he practiced medicine and wrote extensively for local newspapers, publishing a book in 1884, A History of the Grand Traverse Region.
DeWitt was active in politics, both at the state and national levels, and was editor or owner of several newspapers. Wesley served in the 1st Michigan Cavalry from August 1861 to August 1864. A.J. moved to Nebraska in 1867.
Lois H. Leach received her teaching certificate at age fifteen and taught in Genesee County schools. She married three times, first to Frederick Waterman, then William O'Dell, and briefly to Jacob M. Runyan, who became ill and died within days of their wedding. Lois Leach Waterman and her first husband had five children: Edgar, Ella, Hattie, Fred Jr., and Lois. Fred Jr. took his young family to pioneer in Nebraska in 1885. They tried several locations in Nebraska before returning to Michigan in 1895. Fred's son, Edgar Waterman (b. 1880) wrote a manuscript of his childhood memories from these years. The younger Lois Waterman married Edgar M. Armstrong, son of William Armstrong, and had three daughters, Eleanor, Louise, and Harriet (Hattie).
Margaret Leutheuser collected a variety of materials pertaining to her ancestors, notably among the Leach, Waterman and Armstrong families. The collection dates from the 1850s to the 1930s, and includes family correspondence, newspaper articles written by Morgan (M.L.) Leach, and farm account books. The materials are arranged in one Family Papers series by the originator/author of the item.
Subjects:
Armstrong family.; Farm life--Michigan.; Genesee County (Mich.); Grand Traverse Bay Region (Mich.); Leach, M. L. (Morgan Lewis), 1821-; Leach family.; Mundy (Mich.); Nebraska; Temperance; Travelers; United States. Army. Michigan Cavalry Regiment, 1st (1861- 1866); United States. Army. Michigan Cavalry Regiment, 9th (1863-1865); United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.; Waterman family.
Genre/Form:
Scrapbooks
- Family Papers
  - Outline of family relationships (Reel 1)
    Outline of Family Relationships includes brief notes made by Louise Armstrong in 1954, and a genealogical chart created by a BHL staff member from family information found within the collection.
  - Theoda H. Leach (b. 1799-d. 1872)
    The Theoda H. Leach folder contains three letters from her son, Morgan, from 1853 to 1863. The 1853 letter recounts his arrival in Ann Arbor, his expenses and lack of money, and his student class schedule. The 1861 letter announces his arrival in Traverse City and his enthusiasm for building a life there. The 1863 letter is written from camp in Tenessee with the 9th Michigan Cavalry, and laments the lack of reliable war information.
    - Letters to family members, mostly to her daughter Lois H. Leach Waterman
      - 1853-1863 (Reel 1)
      - 1864-1872 (Reel 1)
  - Morgan L. Leach (b. 1821-d. 1910)
    Morgan (M.L.) Leach contributed numerous articles and works of fiction to local newspapers throughout the 1860s-1880s. His scrapbook contains articles on a variety of topics, including temperance and the Wintergreen Temperance Society, religion and Christianity, and the "Woman Question," as well as poetry and short stories. The scrapbook also includes a series of articles contributed by A.J. Leach about his experiences pioneering and living in Nebraska.
    - Letters to his mother, Theoda H. Leach, 1853-1863 (Reel 1)
    - Scrapbook of newspaper articles written by M.L. Leach, 1870s-1880s, 1 volume (Reel 1)
  - Lois H. Leach Waterman O'Dell Runyan (b. 1828-d. 1915)
    Lois H. Leach Waterman O'Dell Runyan kept a scrapbook of articles written by her brother Morgan (M.L.), including his series of Civil War letters as a correspondent for the Republican newspaper (pp. 1-10), a series concerning his travels to the Traverse Bay area in the 1860s (pp. 27-34) and to Nebraska in 1874 (pp. 11-22), his accounts of the Leach family's settlement in Genesee County in the 1830s (pp. 23-25), and other articles, poetry and stories. There are also two folders of correspondence: one of letters written by her mother, Theoda, and one of letters Lois wrote to her grandchildren.
    - Letters to her grandchildren, 1907-1910 (Reel 1)
    - Scrapbook containing newspaper articles written by Morgan L. Leach, 1861-1875, 1 volume (Reel 1)
  - Edgar Waterman (b. 1880)
    Lois's son, Fred Waterman, Jr., married in c. 1879. His son, Edgar Waterman, wrote manuscripts under the pen name Edgar Huntington. Saga of a Nebraska Family is a memoir of his experiences as a child (ages 5-15) pioneering with his family in Nebraska. Due to several years of drought, the family moved to various homesteads in central and western Nebraska before returning permanently to Michigan in 1895.
    - Saga of a Nebraska Family (manuscript), late 1930s (Reel 1)
    - Miscellaneous manuscripts (Reel 1)
  - William Marshall Armstrong
    - Farm account book1865-1874, 1 volume and 9 items (Reel 1)
  - Edgar M. Armstrong
    - Personal papers, 1877-1928 (Reel 1)
    - Scrapbook of newspaper clippings mostly concerning the Civil War and Reconstruction, 1880s, 1 volume (Reel 1)
    - Farm account book, 1886-1889, 1 volume (Reel 1)
  - Hattie Armstrong (b. September 1888)
    - "The Normal Review System of Writing" penmanship workbook (Reel 1)
  - Miscellaneous Letters, 1879-1935 (Reel 1)
  - Scrapbook of newspaper clippings about half concern family members, ca. 1870-1915, 1 volume; (include obituaries of family members) (Reel 1)